Guide to the William E. Irwin Photograph Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Irwin Family, 1885-circa 1930; Series XI; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Irwin Family Groups
    - Exterior portrait of two men and a woman posed standing, as well as a man and woman posed sitting, with a man in the background, identified as the Irwin family, probably at Buck Horn Ranch near Lometa, Lampasas County, Texas, circa 1920; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 12, Folder 864)
      Identified from left to right, posed standing, John Allison Irwin, Mary Frances Elmore Irwin, and Marvin Elmore Irwin; posed sitting, William Edward "Ed" Irwin and Minnie Pearl Irwin Bock Mitchell Sawyers, with William Pinkney "Pink" Irwin in the background
    - View of adults and children at a campsite with a wagon, William Edward "Ed" Irwin and Marvin Elmore Irwin are identified on the left side of the image, probably in Arizona, circa 1920-1930; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 12, Folder 865)
    - View of adults and children at a campsite with automobiles, William Edward "Ed" Irwin and Marvin Elmore Irwin are identified on the left side of the image, probably in Arizona, circa 1920-1930; 1 photographic negative (Box 12, Folder 866)
    - Exterior portrait of three men posed standing and two women posed sitting, identified as members of the Irwin family, on the porch of a home, possibly in Arizona or California, circa 1925-1930; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 12, Folder 867)
      Identified from left to right, posed standing, John Allison Irwin, William Edward "Ed" Irwin, and Marvin Elmore Irwin; posed sitting, Minnie Pearl Irwin Bock Mitchell Sawyers and Mary Frances Elmore Irwin
    - Exterior portrait of three men posed standing and two women posed sitting, identified as members of the Irwin family, on the porch of a home, possibly in Arizona or California, circa 1925-1930; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 12, Folder 868)
    - Exterior portrait of a man posed kneeling by some chickens in front of railcars for the El Paso and Southwestern Railroad, identified as Frank feeding chickens, possibly Francis Newton Irwin, as well as an exterior portrait of a woman and a boy posed standing in front of railcars for the El Paso and Southwestern railroad, circa 1925-1930; 2 unmounted photographic prints (Box 12, Folder 869)
      Inscription on verso of a print: "Frank feeding chickens"
      Inscription on recto of a print: "Me and Alian(?)"
      Ink stamp on versos: "69"
      Francis Newton Irwin (1846-1942) was a brother of William Pinkney "Pink" Irwin
  - Ephemera
    - Receipts from the Texas State Treasurer to William Pinkney "Pink" Irwin, 1885-1892; 7 receipts (Box 12, Folder 870)
    - Registered mail receipts from Francis Richard Lubbock to William Pinkney "Pink" Irwin, 1887-1891 July; 5 receipts (Box 12, Folder 871)
      Francis Richard Lubbock (1815-1905) was Governor of Texas (1861-1863) and Texas State Treasurer (1878-1891)
    - Photograph processing envelope from Irwin's Studio, Douglas, Arizona, circa 1920; 1 envelope (Box 12, Folder 872)
- Collected Photographs, circa 1889-1940; Series XII; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series XII is organized alphabetically by photographer followed by photographs by unidentified photographers
  This series chiefly consists of photographs that depict members of the Irwin family taken by other photographers
  - Croft, Thomas
    Thomas Croft was a photographer in Arkansas City, Kansas
    - Two photographic prints mounted on a board: top print, view of two American Indian women and a child sitting near a tipi in a camp, bottom print, view of a Wichita Indian grass house, probably near Anadarko, Indian Territory, circa 1895; 2 mounted photographic prints (Box 13, Folder 873)
      Photographs probably by Thomas Croft, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma
  - Gill, De Lancey W.
    De Lancey W. Gill (1859-1940) was a painter and photographer with the Division of Illustration in the Bureau of American Ethnology at the Smithsonian Institution
    - Studio portrait of a Cheyenne Indian man, identified as Lame Bull wearing partial native dress with a headdress, 1907 February; 1 mounted photographic print (Box 13, Folder 874)
      Photograph mounted on a board with a benchmark of Lentz in Kingfisher, Oklahoma
  - Haynes, Inc.
    Haynes, Inc., was a photographic firm operated by Frank J. Haynes (1853-1921) and his son, Jack Ellis Haynes (1884-1962), which focused on images of Yellowstone National Park, from 1884 to 1967.
    - View of Crested Pool hot springs, steam, and Castle Geyser, a calcium carbonate cone in Upper Geyser Basin, Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, circa 1926-1940 (Box 13, Folder 875)
      Printed on verso: "10101 Crested Pool and Castle Geyser"
    - View of Yellowstone Lake, as well as Mount Sheridan in the distance, at Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, circa 1926-1940 (Box 13, Folder 876)
      Printed on verso: "10116 Yellowstone Lake, Sheridan Mountain"
    - View of Daisy Geyser in the Upper Geyser Basin of Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, circa 1926-1940 (Box 13, Folder 877)
      Printed on verso: "14031 Daisy Geyser, Yellowstone Park."
    - View of the Lower Falls (Great Falls) of the Yellowstone River in Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, circa 1926-1940 (Box 13, Folder 878)
      Printed on verso: "16253 Lower Fall from Red Rock, Y.N.P."
  - L.L. Cook Company
    L.L. Cook Company was a postcard publishing company in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 1921-1969
    - View of Santa Rita, New Mexico, and its large open pit copper mine, circa 1935 (Box 13, Folder 879)
      Inscription in negative: "B-120, Largest open-pit copper mine in the world, Santa Rita, New Mexico"
    - View of a street in Hurley, New Mexico, circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 880)
      Inscription in negative: "C-198, Street scene, Hurley, New Mexico"
  - Lenny, William J., and William L. Sawyers
    William J. Lenny and William L. Sawyers operated a photography studio in Purcell, Indian Territory, circa. 1889-1891
    - Studio portrait of Ga-to-ka, a Kiowa Indian man, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 881)
      Manuscript Inscription on verso, "W. L. Sawyers"
    - Studio portrait of a Comanche Indian man, identified as Quanah Parker, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 882)
      Manuscript inscription in negative: "Quanah, Commanche Chief"
      Manuscript Inscription on verso: "W. L. Sawyers"
      Manuscript inscription on recto: "Quanah Parker"
    - Studio portrait of three American Indians, probably Comanche Indians, Quanah Parker posed sitting on the left, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 883)
    - Studio portrait of a Kiowa Indian man, identified as Lone Wolf the Elder (Gui-pah-gho or Guipago), circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 884)
      Manuscript inscription in negative: "Lone Wolf, Kiowa Chief"
      Manuscript inscription on recto: "Lone Wolf"
    - Studio portrait of two Apache Indian men, identified as Davako and Dor-con-each-la, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 885)
      Manuscript inscription in negative: "Apache Chiefs Davako and Dor-con-each-la"
    - Portrait of a Kiowa Indian man, identified as Big Tree (Ado-Eette or A'do-eete), circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 886)
      Manuscript inscription on recto: "Big Tree"
    - Studio portrait of a Comanche Indian man, identified as Wild Horse (Kobe), circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 887)
      Manuscript inscription in negative: "Chief Wild Horse"
    - Studio portrait of two Kiowa Indian girls, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 888)
      Manuscript inscriptions in negative: "Kiowa girls" and "40"
    - Portrait of a Kiowa Indian girl posed standing, and a Kiowa Indian woman posed sitting and holding a cradleboard with a infant, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 889)
      Manuscript inscriptions on verso: "W. L. Sawyers" and "Kiowas"
    - Portrait of a Wichita Indian man and two Wichita Indian women, identified as To-wac-a-ny (also known as To-wa-cany Jim) and his wives, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 890)
      Manuscript inscriptions in negative: "Chief To-wac-a-ny and wives, Wichitas" and "13"
    - Fourteen members of the Indian police mounted on horses at Anadarko, Indian Territory, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 891)
      The group include two white men, as well as twelve American Indian men holding rifles
      Manuscript inscription on recto: "Indian Police Force of Anadarko, IT"
    - Six Wichita Indian men playing Three-card Monte on a hill with a view of horses and wagons, circa 1889-1891; 1 mounted photographic print and 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 13, Folder 892)
      Manuscript inscription on recto: "Wichita Sports"
    - View of a Wichita Indian camp, identified as the home of Ska-wa-cer, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 893)
      Manuscript inscriptions in negative: "Ska-wa-cer's Home," "Wichita camp," and "17"
    - Studio portrait of five American Indian men, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 894)
      On mount with benchmark: "Lenny & Sawyers, Purcell, Indian Views"
    - Studio portrait of an American Indian man, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 895)
      Unreadable manuscript inscriptions on recto
    - Studio portrait of a Cheyenne Indian boy, woman, and man, identified as Rain in the Face and his family, circa 1889-1891 (Box 13, Folder 896)
      Manuscript inscription in negative: "Rain in the Face"
      On mount with bench mark on verso for Will Fisher, Atchison, Kansas, as well as additional photographs of American Indians distributed by Fisher
  - Lind, H.
    - View of an automobile on a road with wall of snow on either side in Lassen National Park, California, circa 1940; 1 photographic postcard (Box 13, Folder 897)
      Inscription in negative: "Snow cuts on Lassen Park Highway, Bodine Foto, H. Lind, 116"
      Verso of the postcard include correspondence from Era Bock to Mr. H. P. Early of Hurley, New Mexico, which describes her trip in California, July 5, 1941
  - Scott, Homer
    Homer Scott (1880-1956) was a photographer in El Paso, Texas, and a cinematographer in California
    - View of an American Indian camp with tipis, wagons, and a horse corral, 1911; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 13, Folder 898)
      Inscriptions in negative: "Copyright, 1911, Scott Photo Company" and " 16"
  - Unidentified Photographers
    - Group of views that document the aftermath of a flood, possibly in Arizona or Texas, which show damaged and submerged railroad lines, as well as a view of a herd of cattle, circa 1900; 4 unmounted photographic prints (Box 13, Folder 899)
    - Copy photograph of a studio portrait of an African American woman holding a bar of soap with a nude African American boy across her lap, circa 1903; 1 cabinet photograph (Box 13, Folder 900)
      Original image includes printed caption, "De biggis washin I dun dis week," as well as "Copyright 1903, Merchants Pubg Co., Chicago"
    - View of Wilhelm II (1859-1941), German Emperor (Kaiser) and King of Prussia, in military uniform walking with a clergyman, circa 1915; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 13, Folder 901)
      Inscription on recto: "Kaiser Wilhelm"
    - View of swimmers in a lake and on a dock, as well as spectators on the lakeshore, probably in the American Southwest, circa 1920; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 13, Folder 902)
    - Overview of a town, probably in the American Southwest, circa 1926-1940; 1 photographic postcard (Box 13, Folder 903)
    - View of Mount Charleston in the Spring Mountains mountain range, Nevada, 1938 April 20; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 13, Folder 904)
      Pencil inscription on verso: "Mt. Charleston, Apr. 20, 38"
      Ink stamp on verso: "62"
- Oversize Photographs, 0.25; (1 box)
  Contains oversize material from various series.
  Arranged geographically followed by a studio portrait of William Edward "Ed" Irwin
  - Arizona
    - Gila River
      - View of a dirt road parallel to the Gila River in Arizona, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 905)
    - Guadalupe Canyon
      - Overhead view of a hunting camp with a wall tent, two women, and three men in Guadalupe Canyon, Arizona, 1910 November (Box 14, Folder 906)
      - View of a hunting camp with a wall tent, two women, and four men in Guadalupe Canyon, Arizona, 1910 November (Box 14, Folder 907)
    - Lee's Ferry
      - View of the Colorado River at Lee's Ferry, Arizona, circa 1904-1935 (Box 14, Folder 908)
    - Needle's Eye
      - View of the Needle's Eye, an arch carved through a rock formation on the highway between Silver City and Clifton, New Mexico, with an automobile, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 909)
    - Painted Desert
      - View of petrified wood and a desert landscape, probably in the petrified forest in the Painted Desert, Arizona, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 910)
      - View of petrified wood and a desert landscape, probably in the petrified forest in the Painted Desert, Arizona, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 911)
    - Rincon Mountains
      - View of a desert landscape with Carnegiea gigantea (saguaro) cactus in Arizona, with the Rincon Mountains in the distance, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 912)
    - Santa Catalina Mountains
      - View of a desert landscape with Carnegiea gigantea (saguaro) cactus in Arizona with the Santa Catalina Mountains in the distance, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 913)
      - View of a desert landscape with Carnegiea gigantea (saguaro) cactus in Arizona with the Santa Catalina Mountains in the distance, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 914)
    - Yuma
      - View of sand dunes near Yuma, Arizona, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 915)
    - Unidentified Locations in Arizona
      - View of a desert landscape with Carnegiea gigantea (saguaro) cactus in southern Arizona, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 916)
      - View of a desert landscape with Carnegiea gigantea (saguaro) cactus in southern Arizona, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 917)
      - View of a desert landscape with Yucca brevifolia (yucca palm or Joshua Tree) in Arizona, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 918)
      - View of a desert landscape with mountains in the distance, probably in Arizona, circa 1904-1945 (Box 14, Folder 919)
  - Mexico
    - Mexican-American Border Region
      - Exterior portrait of Venustiano Carranza de la Garza posed sitting and surrounded by three women and nine men posed standing, probably in the Mexican-American Border Region, circa 1913-1915 (Box 14, Folder 920)
      - Exterior portrait of a man, identified as William Edward "Ed" Irwin, and a woman, identified as probably Carrie Matilda "Tillie" Allen Irwin, posed kneeling with rifles near the carcasses of two pumas in the Mexican-American Border region, 1910 November (Box 14, Folder 921)
      - Exterior portrait of a woman, identified as probably Carrie Matilda "Tillie" Allen Irwin, posed sitting on a log with rifle and looking through binoculars, near the carcasses of two pumas in the Mexican-American Border region, 1910 November (Box 14, Folder 922)
      - Exterior portrait of two men, man on left identified as William Edward "Ed" Irwin, posed standing with rifles with a puma over Irwin's shoulder and a deer carcass on the ground, in the Mexican-American Border region, 1910 November (Box 14, Folder 923)
      - Exterior portrait of a man, identified as William Edward "Ed" Irwin, and a woman, identified as probably Carrie Matilda "Tillie" Allen Irwin, with their backs to the camera and each carrying a puma carcass over their shoulder and holding rifles in the Mexican-American Border region, 1910 November (Box 14, Folder 924)
      - Exterior portrait of two men from behind posed mounted on two horses with two pack donkeys on a dirt trail, probably in the Mexican-American Border Region, circa 1910 (Box 14, Folder 925)
  - Texas
    - El Paso County
      - View of a herd of goats and a goat herder, near El Paso, Texas, circa 1893-1903 (Box 14, Folder 926)
    - Kimble County
      - Exterior portrait of a man, identified as William Pinkney "Pink" Irwin, posed standing and holding a rifle, as well as the reins of a horse, over the carcass of a dead deer, in Kimble County, Texas, circa 1893-1903 (Box 14, Folder 927)
      - View of eight deer carcasses lying on the ground in a hunting camp with two men skinning them, identified as William Pinkney "Pink" Irwin and Dave Jones in Kimble County, Texas, circa 1894 (Box 14, Folder 928)
  - Studio portrait of William Edward "Ed" Irwin
    - Studio bust portrait of William Edward "Ed" Irwin with a lapel pin with a masonic emblem, circa 1910 (Box 14, Folder 929)